<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bharath M R</title><link href="www.catchmrbharath.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="www.catchmrbharath.in/feeds/Life.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>www.catchmrbharath.in/</id><updated>2012-10-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Learning to walk before you run</title><link href="www.catchmrbharath.in/posts/Life/2012-Oct-24/learning-to-walk-before-you-run/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Bharath M R</name></author><id>tag:www.catchmrbharath.in,2012-10-24:posts/Life/2012-Oct-24/learning-to-walk-before-you-run/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;tags [Programming, learning]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look back at the last 4 years of my engineering life, I feel I haven't
done anything worthwhile. Compared to the amount of learning I did in my pre
-college years, the last 4 years look like nothing. I did a lot of things in
these four years, but I cannot claim to be an expert in any of them. During
my school days, I was really good at what I learnt, maybe the best among my
peers. One might argue that the feeling you have is, because you have the most
competitive and talented peers . But that's not true. There was
something that changed after clearing JEE and that was trying to run before
you walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always want to see the whole picture before learning something, i.e. what do
I get to do after I learn these stuff. In school education, you always know
what you are going to do with the things you learnt, but it is not the case
with college education. The first two years of my undergraduate studies, was
spent doing courses like Networks and systems, Digital systems, Analog
circuits, Control systems etc. Nobody gave me an idea on where these things are
going to be used during these period. Even though it was interesting, I felt the pace
of these courses was slow. I was asked to calculate the Fourier transforms of
infinitely many functions just for the sake of it. I didn't know where these
functions are going to be used. So I started spending time on other things. One
of them that got me interested is programming. You could see the output
immediately and there were examples of huge systems built with the things that
I was learning. But two years of clearing the courses with very little effort
had made me cocky and overconfident. I had lost the patience to go through
something with care. I wanted to become an awesome programmer as quickly as
possible. I wanted to create GUI's, so I started learning Java.(Then I felt it
was the thing that we can make GUI's with.). But again I was impatient.
I started learning the language and I went through the initial part really very
fast and lost my interest after I started encountering some things which were
dependent on the fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never realized the basic mistake I was making. Thinking that I knew Java
pretty well, I started experimenting with android development. I built some
good apps by googling things and figuring out, but never ever tried to learn
the basics. I was just trying to run. When you make an extreme effort to run,
you will fall at a distance from your starting point, which gives you the
illusion that you made some progress, but actually you are at the same point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of my fourth year, I put some effort and got into Google summer
of code. It was a stroke of luck i.e. my programming capabilities were still
bad. I think my organisation decided to go with me because of the amount of
effort that I put in getting my application done. This was a large project and
I think this is the place where I learnt most of the things I know today.
I learnt to write decently good code, learnt on how to communicate via email,
and other things. This is one place where I learnt things from scratch and
started experimenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People think that I know things really well, but thats not true. People say
that I am going through the [Imposter's syndrome]{www.http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome},
but I am not. I am still an awful programmer who knows things because he reads
a lot of [Hacker News]{www.news.ycombinator.com}. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has to change. I have to start to relearn things. One thing that GSoC
taught me is that it is really necessary to spend some time before you become
good at it. You need to walk before you run. Maybe its too late, but there is
only one path that I can take, that is to relearn things and not go with the
flow.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>